question that keeps coming up various
places about about
relationships.
Mhm. Yeah. What is
Yeah. What is
romantic relationship?
Relationships, intimate relationships.
Mhm. So, we're not not all relationships are
So, we're not not all relationships are
bad.
Well, depends from what point of view
you look at it. Yeah.
Passionate, intimate, intimate,
sexual,
romantic relationships. Is that good or bad?
relationships. Is that good or bad?
Right. Right. Well, depends on what your
goals are.
Feels nice.
Depends on what your goals are.
Feeling nice might be bad.
Mhm. But that's your goal.
But that's your goal.
Exactly. Exactly.
If that's your goal, then then it's not
bad for you. But so you have to
recognize and what what do you want
from your life?
Do you want to find
a relationship, invest effort in it,
develop it, cultivate it, or do you want
to practice the dharma?
So if you don't want to practice da or
if you only want to practice da
partially, then it's not correct to say
that the relationships are bad because
you wouldn't see that.
But you cannot expect then oh so my
relationships are not bad but I can
still practice the dharma. You have to
recognize they're mutually exclusive.
But should you not cultivate any?
Should you not practice the dharma?
That's then the question and that's up
to you.
like up to everyone individually. If you
want to practice the dharma, then yes,
relationships are unh wholesome. They
are the opposite of that goal. If you
don't want to practice the dharma, then
doesn't matter what I say.
Yeah. But if you practice the dharma and
then you don't cultivate relationships,
then you'll be lonely and suffer.
Yeah. But at least you try to practice.
Yeah. You can't have it all.
You can't have it all.
Yeah. So you either choose the worldly
goals or you choose to overcome the
world in which case means you cannot
invest the same effort in the worldly
goals. It's it's it's it's sort of
contradicting each other.
So the question really it's not a right
question to say oh are relationships
bad? It's more like should we all practice
It's more like should we all practice
the dhamma or not or should I practice
the dhamma or not? If the answer is yes,
then you got your answers for all the
relationships, sexual or otherwise, they
are bad
because they're against the principle of
dharma. So if you know you want to practice
So if you know you want to practice
dharma but now wonder why a relationship
bad against the point of view of the dharma,
against the point of view of the dharma,
well the answer is you cannot have a
relationship, you cannot have intimacy
without desire.
You cannot have desire without lust.
And dharma is freedom from lust, freedom
from desire, freedom from intimacy,
freedom from depending on anything
external. So, and can you have a relationship with
So, and can you have a relationship with
others non-externally? Impossible. Can
you have a relationship with others
without having desire towards them?
Impossible. Can you have relationship
sexual or otherwise without lust towards
their form externally? Impossible. I
mean even ask yourself
can you be in love with somebody without
being physically as well having lust
towards their form doesn't matter if
their form is beautiful or ugly what
matters is you want that form could you
have desire and lust towards the
opposite sex for example if the form
does not exist
inconceivable you can try to be in love with the idea
you can try to be in love with the idea
but even then that idea assumes a
certain form which is how you find that
idea in others when you fall in love and
so on because you already carry that
framework template of this is what I
value and then you recognize it embodied
in others but it has to be external
which means it has to require
infatuation lust and desire
because dharma can only be practiced in
solitude there is no group practice
and whenever the Buddha was numerous
Just take a pick
months to go mons to go in solitude and
be alone physically alone dwell most of
the time in solitude not in company even
if it's company of other like-minded
people company is company
so can you have a relationship without
company impossible
which means if you have relationship you
can't practice the dharma
And that's saying that uh where there is
intimacy lust for finds the opening and
it comes from a really intense suit.
Can you have intimacy without company?
So if there's no company, no room for
intimacy. If there is no intimacy, how can there
If there is no intimacy, how can there
be lust arising?
So why are relationships bad from the
dharma point of view is because they
require company intimacy? intimacy?
No company,
right? Which results in intimacy which results
Which results in intimacy which results
in lust.
Yeah. So even if you live withdrawn from
relationships, if you cultivate
relationship mentally
and wish for it or refuse to give it up,
you're living in company.
You are living in intimacy.
So yeah, that's why they're bad.
Everything else that can come out of
that relationship, good or bad, is
secondary because all of that is founded
upon the fact that it requires company
of others.
But there is obviously if you want to
live a worldly life, then there are ways
to cultivate good relationships.
Of course, but that's not what we're
talking about.
Yeah. So it's not
So it's not
so you can't those are two different
things. So you can't use two different
things to extrapolate the context that
would then apply to both because they're
mutually exclusive. So if you don't want
to practice the dharma then the
statement that all relationships are bad
because they require company does not
apply to you because you don't want to
practice for aranchip
but that's also mean that disqualifies
you from talking about practice towards
aranchip from talking about dharma and that's
from talking about dharma and that's
really the problem like same like when
people like you know oh lay life or a
monk it's not about that doesn't matter
if you're a lay person or you're a monk
whether relation relationships or not.
What matters is whether you took
practice of dharma as your goal. If so,
then it doesn't matter whether you wear
robes or not. What matters is whether
you pursue sensuality or not.
And if the goal of dharma is taken up,
pursue sensuality has to be abandoned.
Again, doesn't matter whether you're a
layman or not.
So that's where things are rooted. But
the the problem or rather the the worst
thing is the view that I have taken the
dharma but then at the same time assume that
but then at the same time assume that
you can still engage with sensuality and
company and so on which are two mutually
because you're a layman.
No being a layman does not be does not
mean uh not being celibate.
If being a layman means not being a
celibate then basically if you become a
celibate even without wearing a robe you
are not a layman and that's absolutely
fine. You can regard yourself with that.
That's why the gura used the word arry
sana even for ordained or non-ordained
people but people with the right view or
more people who have overcome atavada
people who have overcome atavada
sensuality and so on
and they were not ordained yet they were
the sa of that kind but he did not use
that to include people who were sensual
people who are not practicing towards
dham people who don't have the right
view nobody shorter than sodana belongs
to well dhamari sadosari they belong to
aryas as well which is the sodapana
without still quite not realizing the
fruit of it.
So a sign that you are
practicing practicing for intimacy
is something Yeah. I don't know. I got
this thought that if you are trying to
get personal
some well it's intimate.
Yeah. Can you get again? Can you get
personal with someone without that
someone? Impossible.
Impossible.
So, you're already seeking things out
externally, even if you don't find them.
And but that is that is regarded in in
many Buddhist circles as kind of the
practice is kind of developing this
special friendship deep
personal intimate
intimate friendship.
Yeah. Cuz they don't really know where
the practice is.
And that that intimacy opens you up and
opens the other person up
to lust.
Yeah. To lust. Eventually
it gets it's same in Christianity in
like Christian mysticism. Basically you
develop relationship with God with your
imaginary friend. You develop a fullon
relationship of love and devotion. So the only reason
of love and devotion. So the only reason
that that relationship that relationship
does not become lustful is because the
form of the other does not exist. So it
remains left hollow basically. But the
attitude is still there the same
emotional infatuated infatuated
dependent.
So you have to recognize that dharma is
against all of that practice of dharma.
So if you do recognize that then you
realize that the other views the values
towards relationship towards company
towards sensuality sensuality is a form
of company as the Buddha said um all of
those relationship are contradictory
with the goal that you value. So you can
then choose to ignore that contradiction
and then feel qualified in talking about
practicing towards arahanchip and not
even being celibate
or you cannot ignore that these two
things contradict and then make the
effort to be celibate and develop that
which you yourself value more freedom
from suffering.
So the worst thing is to develop the
view they will ignore the contradiction
of your own existence. I value freedom
from suffering, but I'm also not
celibate. I value freedom from
suffering, full transparency, undoing of
my being, abandoning all the ascles. Oh,
but I also love company of others.
Those are plain contradictions.
So, should we all abandon the world and
practice other? That's not up to you.
Do whatever you want to do. But if you
do, you have to bend the world.
Yeah. If you don't want to do it, that's fine.
If you don't want to do it, that's fine.
It's on you. Your actions, your results.
But don't try to kind of ignore the
contradiction and then sort of
refabricate and try to justify that you
don't have to abandon the world and you
can still practice for the freedom of
the world, freedom of yourself from the
world. Well, that's a contradiction in
terms.
is it's a simile of the saw and one of
the sections the first section
uh there's a monk called Paguna
and he was entangled with the nuns so he
was quite intimate with the nuns if any
monk spoke in sprays of those nuns in
his presence so he was still a proper
monk so which means he was still keeping
the rules
so he wasn't physical with those nuns or
anything else
he just intimate with them. So
he was intimate. He was friendly.
Friendly having friendship and so on.
having friendship and so on.
So nothing sexual may you know overtly.
No cuz that would have been mentioned.
Yeah. So he was just entangled intimate with
So he was just entangled intimate with
them so to speak. If any other monk
spoke in displays of the nuns in his
presence, he would be angered and
displeased and would make an issue
out of it. And if any monk spoke in
dispraise of him in the presence of the
nuns, they would be angered, displeased, and
they would be angered, displeased, and
would make an issue out of it,
that's how much he was spending time
entangled with the nuns.
Yeah. So,
So,
could that entanglement arise if he
didn't spend time with them?
Yeah. Could that displeasure?
Could then everything else that arose
from the entanglement arise if he did
not spend time in their company?
Impossible. And by the way, they were all very
And by the way, they were all very
like-minded.
I mean, they were so like-minded. I bet
they clicked right away. Same values,
same goals, monk, none. Same same, same
same. I'm celibate, you celebrate. Perfect for
I'm celibate, you celebrate. Perfect for
each other.
Exactly. Exactly.
It's the company that is the problem.
Mhm. Because often people try to justify the
Because often people try to justify the
company on account of a greater goal and
greater purpose that we all partake in.
Oh, let's all come and sit together in
this meditation.
Yeah. So that through that attachment
aversion is born.
Of course. Yeah.
If someone tries to hurt those nuns, you
get you will you will not be able to be
you will you will not be able to be
indifferent. Um
Um
so then the the Buddha
called went to speak to him says come.
And uh
so the Buddha questions him, is it true,
Paguna, that you are spending too much
time with the nuns? And
well, what is time anyway?
Spending too much time with you
basically. He says, yes, Lord says,
aren't you a clansman who has gone forth
from the home life into homelessness out
of conviction?
Exactly. Aren't you the one? Yeah.
Who has abandoned your whole previous
life on a kind of valuing dharma and
freedom from suffering which requires
freedom from company and intimacy.
Aren't you the one who already realized
that that's valuable? Hence, you're a
monk now.
Yes, I am. And yet you're doing the
contradictory things now to your own
values. Yeah. Yes. He says it's not fitting for
Yeah. Yes. He says it's not fitting for
you.
It's not fitting. It does not fit the
values you took upon yourself. If you
were not a clansman who has abandoned
his lay life and became a monk, I don't
care. Do what you like.
But it's not right. That's why exactly
he's telling
that's why it's not right. He says, "So
if anyone speaks in disprays of the nuns
in your presence, even then you should
abandon any desire related to the
household life and any thoughts related
to the household life. And even then you
should train yourself. My mind will be
unaffected and I will say no evil words.
I will remain sympathetic to that
person's welfare.
I will not lose the framework of non-
ill will,
dispassion and so on.
Yeah. If anyone gives hurts those nuns
with a stone or a hand or a rod or a
knife in your presence right there, you should
in your presence right there, you should
abandon any desire and says the same
thing. Abandon all ill will towards that those
Abandon all ill will towards that those
people.
Exactly. If anyone should speak in
dispays of you in your presence, even
then you should abandon desires.
If anyone gives you a hit with a hand or
a stone or a rod or a knife,
you should not abandon all
let alone what like what to be said for
other people.
Yeah. Cine for others.
So the criteria then is not whether
you're a layman or a monk. The criteria
is whether you want to practice dumb or
not.
Should I be doing this?
Yeah. That's so should lay people be
celibate. Yes. If they want to practice
dharma for arahanchip
if they say well I don't want to pray
dham for arahanchip fine but then you're
not going to get to talk about dharma of
arahanchship cuz you refuse to practice
on that level by refusing to be celerate
as simple as that
but I want to have a view of practicing
towards aranchip and at the same time do
the opposite of the requirement for
practice for aranchip well that's why
you're a living contradiction
and you don't want to be and you find
for yourself. Wait, am I a contradiction
to my own values? That's what the
Buddhas ask him. Aren't you the man who
left his whole life on account of these
values? So why are you contradicting
them? They don't fit your own values.
It's okay. They do not fit your own
values.
and you realize oh the only way you're
contradicting yourself is because you
ignore or you turn a blind eye to the
extent of your own values
and that's the worst thing
by turning a blind eye you develop a
view that you can have both I am
qualified to talk about aranchip and
practice aranchip and I also don't have
to be a celibate
and deep down if you look at it closely
you already know it's a contradiction in
terms but I just want to
but I just want to
have everything go my own way if I
believe. Well, it's not even that rational. It's
Well, it's not even that rational. It's
more like no, I just don't want to
expose myself to any form of discomfort.
So, I just always go with the path of
least resistance on the emotional kind
cuz it it's going to cause some friction
internally if you recognize that your values
if you recognize that your values
contradict things you want to do. Ah, I
need to practice sense restraint now
because it contradicts the values.
And that is unpleasant. So I could
either endure that discomfort and grow
out of it or I can ignore or try to
remold my values to allow me to engage
in things I want to do guilt-free. It
always comes down to that always.
So if lay person means sensuality,
relationship, company, dhamma does not
apply to you.
But if a lay person gives up dependence
on company, intimacy, lust,
relationship, sensuality, time applies
to you. You partake in the novel SA. But
you can't have it both ways.
Despite what contemporary sort of
teachings that you selectively pick up
might tell you, read the sutas and
you'll see for yourself.
Cuz you have people these days say, "Ah,
you can be arant and have sexual
intercourse. You can have unpleasant
desire and be free from suffering.
Yes, exactly.
Towards that
you can feel the burning the desire and
be free from desire at the same time.
That's pretty much what they're saying.
Freeing free being free from desire. You
can engage with all desires.
How does that work?
Yeah, that sounds good.
Yeah. only to the one who is not free
from desire.
If you have an inkling of freedom from
desire, you realize actually even that
does not sound good.
Yeah. Yeah. And there was that other
suit similar. Actually, that wasn't
necessarily in in um in the context of
President Dam. It was just in the
context why intimacy is unh wholesome
because it makes you dependable
on even a greater extent of things that
are not in your control.
Same love for children, your spouse, if
something happens to them, you cannot
not be affected.
Yeah. So you recognize that, oh, this is a
So you recognize that, oh, this is a
liability. like I'm already liable to
all this suffering simply on account of
my own existence let alone incorporating
existence of others into my own
dependence into my own existence that
makes you really really that's why the
children are the greatest source of
suffering as duba said because if
something happens to your child there's
no way you'll be economous there's no
way and the suit I'm thinking of was
that when um he gives the example why
intimacy and love is cause of suffering
was the man in love with a woman
infatuated having lust towards her and
he as wouldn't that like if that man
were to see that woman laughing and
giggling with another man
would he suffer on account of that sight
he's like yes of course why cuz his mind
is bound with her form by last
infatuation and now that form is
basically given to somebody else at
least in his mind as in he has no
control over it.
Yeah. It's extreme displeasure not
because of what she's doing but because
of his bound with her that requires
certain behavior that she's now going
against. and says if that man has wisdom
he will reflect thus he would say h my
mind is bound by infatuation and lust
love towards that woman that's why when
I see her with another man I experience
extreme pain and suffering what if I
were to undo that lust and aversion lust
and infatuation towards that woman then
he sets himself upon not cultivating
that lust not welcoming that infatuation
not clinging to it basically allowing it
to endure but basically overcoming it
not fueling it anymore. And then later
on on another occasion, he doesn't have
lust and infatuation with that woman.
And if he were to see that woman
laughing and giggling, would he
experience pain and suffering? No. Cuz
there's nothing binding him to that
form. Nothing requiring a certain set of
behavior of that form. Thus suffering
cannot arise. Same. Could you suffer a
kind of losing a child if you don't have
a child?
Impossible. If you have a child, could
you theoretically overcome any
attachment towards a child? Yes. If you
were to overcome the slightest
attachment, slightest defatuation,
slightest love towards your own child,
could you suffer on account of anything
happening to that child? Impossible. So,
you have a choice. You'll ignore that
possibility of development and cultivate
the intimacy,
maintain it, ignore it, which is a form
of maintaining it already.
But then you make yourself liable to
anything wholesome or unh wholesome that
can affect you.
Yeah. So why don't why don't I suffer
when other children die or otheract
people's mothers? Well, there was that there was
mothers? Well, there was that there was
that sut where the wood was sitting in
the forest with the monks and he said
monks would you be upset if people come
in now in this woodland where we're
sitting and start collecting these twigs
and branches and burning them and
breaking them. What? No, we wouldn't be
upset. Why would we be upset? Who cares
about these discarded branches? That's
how you should regard your own body.
your own life
let alone body of others and and which
are already secondary to your point of
view
literally like discarded twigs and
branches that's how you that's how you
need to regard
your your whole experience as a whole
and that's how we'll experience this
passion towards that
so it's attachment to others other
things you're exposing yourself so much
more you're just expanding your exposure
you're just expanding your exposure
well also exactly you cannot be attached
in love, infatuated with others without
ignoring your own existence to that
extent without ignoring your own liability.
without ignoring your own liability.
Like your own existence makes you liable
to suffering on account of things you're
not in control of. You need to ignore
that in order to allow yourself to
proliferate far enough to actually
incorporate others in your love and
infatuation. It's impossible to become infatuated and
It's impossible to become infatuated and
in love if you don't forget the context
of your own existence which is a
perilous situation.
So you need to be repetitively ignoring
your own nature of your own situation
which is impermanent and suffering in
order to basically establish your mind
upon other people.
I remember someone saying that he he was
practicing meta
for many many years.
M
meta in a traditional sense
and uh but when he had a child
that just went right out the window
because it was when the child was
bullied at school.
Oh yeah.
But he wanted to just
destroy the other children you know.
Yep. Because if you were to practice
matter, you wouldn't have been engaging in acts
you wouldn't have been engaging in acts
of love, lust, sensuality, and
everything else.
Cuz all of that means acting out of how
you feel.
And if you act out of how you feel means
you're not economous towards what you
feel. So there's no matter there. There's no
So there's no matter there. There's no
framework.
Yeah. He was practicing the wrong type of meta
He was practicing the wrong type of meta
actually.
Yeah. Which really isn't matter. Yeah.